<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Thomas Campbell</title><link href="http://thomascampbell.me.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thomascampbell.me.uk/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thomascampbell.me.uk/</id><updated>2015-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Axelrod Python Strategies</title><link href="http://thomascampbell.me.uk/axelrod.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Thomas Campbell</name></author><id>tag:thomascampbell.me.uk,2015-08-05:axelrod.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Meta Hunter and Fool me Once&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the tournament on Axelrod-Python is run, a boxplot is generated and
displayed on the Readme of the repository so that everyone can see the winning
strategies. As of June 2015 there were 66 strategies submitted to
Axelrod-Python. The boxplot looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/strategies_boxplot_june_2015.png" alt="Strategies boxplot from
June 2015" style="width: 800px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, in June 2015 "Meta Hunter” was the current winning strategy on
Axelrod-Python. This strategy was one of the more complicated strategies of the
tournament. It worked by combining various “hunters” that hunted specific mean
strategies and defected against them. Individually these hunters did not perform
particularly well. However when combined as “Meta Hunter” it proved to be
extremely effective and was the winning strategy for quite a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other strategy that even came close to “Meta Hunter” was “Fool me
Once”. This strategy was one of the most simple strategies in the tournament. It
cooperated unless the opponent had defected more than once. If the opponent had
defected more than once then it would defect forever. It was extremely simple
and yet very effective. Both of these strategies were “nice”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance it may be easy to say that “Meta Hunter” and “Fool me Once”  are
very different strategies. However on closer inspection they appear to be more
similar than you might think. “Meta Hunter” hunts individual mean strategies and
when it finds them it will defect forever. “Fool me Once” bypasses individual
strategies and will just generically defect against anything that defects
unprovoked. The end outcome is the same. So even though “Fool me Once” is only a
few lines of code, it does almost the same thing as “Meta Hunter”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;BackStabber&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the summer holidays I found that I had a bit of spare time. So, naturally
I decided to submit some strategies to Axelrod-Python. I saw that “Fool me Once”
was so simple and so effective and decided to base my new strategy on it. The
first thing I noticed was that every strategy should defect on the last 2 turns
unconditionally. This is because defecting is better than cooperating whether
the opponent cooperates or defects. The reason that cooperating can be
beneficial is to prevent a defection cycle. On the last 2 turns there is no
danger of a defection cycle because by the time your opponent retaliates there
will only be 1 turn left. Therefore defecting on the last 2 turns is better in
every situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to my strategies nature of cruelty at the end of the round, I named it
“BackStabber”. And sure enough it won the tournament by a very slim margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However I then improved the strategy even more. Instead of defecting forever
after my opponent's second defection, I increased it to their fourth. At first I
did not understand why this improved the strategy. Surely it made it more
inefficient? It did. But it greatly improved its performance against strategies
that cooperated most of the time but randomly defected every now and then. It
meant that Backstabber could be in a cooperation cycle with these strategies for
much longer, rather than defecting and being in a defection cycle. Its
performance was improved against these strategies so much that it greatly
outweighed the slight inefficiencies it caused against all of the other
strategies. This improvement propelled Backstabber to the top of the tournament
by a much bigger margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aggravater&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the biggest factor in how well a strategy performs is how well it is
suited to it's environment. Because of this I decided to "tweak" the
environment. I did this by creating a strategy that was deliberately designed so
that Backstabber would perform well against it while the other strategies did
not. I decided to take advantage of the fact that Backstabber would forgive the
first 3 defections from any strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy I created was not designed to win the tournament. It was a pawn. It
was designed to "sacrifice" itself to help Backstabber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy worked by defecting on the first 3 turns to "aggravate" the
opponent. It then would cooperate until the opponent defected. If they defected
it would then defect forever. I named the strategy "Aggravater".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason the strategy worked was because Backstabber would not defect because
Aggravater would not reach the limit of 4 defections. After the first 3 turns
they would begin an endless cooperation cycle and maximise their score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, other strategies (like Fool Me Once and Meta Hunter) would defect early
because of the 3 defections at the beginning. This would cause a defection cycle
and minimize their scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result was that Backstabber's average score became even higher than any
other strategy's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Double-Crosser&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/strategies_payoff_no_doublecrosser.png" alt="Strategies
payoff" style="width: 800px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>