<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Thomas Campbell</title><link>http://thomascampbell.me.uk/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thomascampbell.me.uk/feeds/thomas-campbell.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>An Introduction to Axelrod-Python</title><link>http://thomascampbell.me.uk/axelrod-intro.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently started contributing to a project called Axelrod-Python and have
found it very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axelrod-Python is a python project dedicated to recreating Robert Axelrod’s
original iterated prisoner's dilemma tournaments in the 1980's. The Github
repository can be viewed &lt;a href="https://github.com/Axelrod-Python/Axelrod"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prisoner's dilemma is a two player game theory exercise where both players have the choice of defecting or cooperating. They do not know what the other player will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they both cooperate they will both receive 3 points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they both defect they will both receive 1 point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If one cooperates and one defects then the defector will receive 5 points and the cooperator will receive 0 points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the game is to maximise your score over 200 rounds. The only information available to you is your opponent's history so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Axelrod-Python strategies are submitted as python code. Each strategy will
play every other in a tournament and the strategy with the highest average score
wins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axelrod's original tournament was used to simulate evolution and investigate how
cooperation can evolve over time. This project aims to reproduce that work. You
can read about Axelrod's original tournaments and learn more about the
prisoner's dilemma
&lt;a href="http://axelrod.readthedocs.org/en/latest/background.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axelrod-Python is an open source project and so anyone can contribute. If you
want to contribute, there are instructions on how to on the repository
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Axelrod-Python/Axelrod"&gt;Readme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Thomas Campbell</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:thomascampbell.me.uk,2015-08-11:axelrod-intro.html</guid></item><item><title>Nice and Mean Strategies</title><link>http://thomascampbell.me.uk/axelrod-nice-and-mean-strategies.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One way of grouping strategies is be splitting them into “nice” and “mean”
strategies. Nice strategies will never defect before their opponent has defected
and so will never defect first. Hence if two nice strategies play each other,
the outcome will always be cooperation on every turn. This is called a
“cooperation cycle”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mean strategy is a strategy that may defect before the opponent. Any
randomised strategy is by definition mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of a nice strategy is that when both players cooperate they
maximise their points as a pair. They receive 6 points overall, which is more
than any other situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mean strategies will anger other strategies by defecting. If two strategies end
up defecting against each other on every turn it is called a “defection cycle”.
This is the worst possible outcome as the pair only receives 2 points overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore it is easy to see that a cooperation cycle is desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his original tournaments Axelrod concluded that nice strategies will normally
outperform mean strategies. This is because the winner of both tournaments was
"Tit for Tat" which was a nice strategy. Tit for Tat worked by cooperating on
the first round and then copying the opponents last decision. It was a very
simple strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Thomas Campbell</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:thomascampbell.me.uk,2015-08-11:axelrod-nice-and-mean-strategies.html</guid></item></channel></rss>